A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Thomas Milton Rivers, Administrative Correspondence, Series 2 FA221
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Thomas Milton Rivers, Administrative Correspondence, Series 2
1937-1959
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA221
1.32 Cubic Feet 3 boxes. Extent volume is approximate.
Biographical/Historical note
The newly adopted By-Laws of 1953 provided for an elected Vice-President who was a member of the Board of Trustees. Thomas Milton Rivers was elected the first Vice-President of the newly constituted Board of Trustees and served as Director of The Institute, Director of the Department of Laboratories and Director of the Hospital until his retirement in 1955.
August 1955 amendments to the By-Laws abolished the elected Vice-President and the requirement which provided that he be a member of the Board of Trustees and called for one or more appointed Vice-Presidents. Further amendment, January 25, 1956 provided that the Board of Trustees elect one or more Vice-Presidents to discharge such functions as may be assigned to them by the President or by resolution duly accepted at any meeting.
Between 1955 and 1959 Frank Lappin Horsfall, Jr. held the position of Vice-President for Clinical Studies; between 1955 and 1964 Douglas Whitaker served as Vice-President for Administration (between 1961-64 changed to Vice-President for Academic Administration). In 1964/65 Maclyn McCarty was elected Vice-President with special responsibilities in the clinical sciences. He is at the same time, Physician-in-Chief. In 1965 Carl Pfaffmann was elected Vice-President and Professor to develop a program of research and graduate instruction in the behavioral and social sciences. In 1969/70 a third Vice-President was added. This position carries with it the role of Secretary to the Board of Trustees and was filled by Charles Eugene Sunderlin.
In 1972 the University trustees elected Rodney W. Nichols to a new post of Vice-President for Program planning. He had been the first Director of the Office of Program Planning and Development.
In 1973 Albert Gold was named Vice-President for Academic Resources. As Vice-President he also retains his responsibilities relating to Junior faculty (Director of Postdoctoral Affairs) with additional duties in connection with organization, operation and planning at the University.
In 1974, effective September 15, Maclyn McCarty retired as Physician-in-Chief of the Hospital, which post was then filled by Dr. Attalah Kappas.
June 30, 1976 Eugene Sunderlin retired as vice-president of the RU.
June 1978 Dr. Albert Gold resigned from the University and October 1978 Drs. McCarty and Pfaffmann having reached retirement age resigned their positions as Vice-President. Mr. Rodney Nichols was elected to a new position of executive Vice-President and Mr. David J. Lyons was elected to a new position as Vice-President and Controller with new managerial responsibilities.
Other Finding Aids
FA902 Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Thomas Milton Rivers, Biographical Material, Series 6
Arrangement
Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Thomas Milton Rivers is arranged in two series:
Series 2: Administrative Correspondence Series 6: Biographical Material
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 341-2
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for researchd. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Vice President, 1953-1955.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: correspondence.
Sunderlin, Eugene; Whitaker, Douglas Merritt; Horsfall, Frank Lappin; Lyons, David J.; Rivers, Thomas M. (Thomas Milton); Pfaffmann, Carl; Shannon, James A. (James Augustine)
- Administrative Correspondence, 1937-1959; 2; 1.32 Cubic Feet 3 boxes. Extent volume is approximate.
  - Administrative correspondence, 1937-1959; 1 box
    Scope and Contents
    The correspondence is, in the main, from his position as Director of the Hospital though it extends through the period of vice-presidency. It deals, primarily, with recommendations for appointments, research projects and plans for meetings.
    Biographical/Historical note
    Thomas Milton Rivers became Director of the Department of the Hospital upon the retirement of Rufus Cole in 1937 and was named the first Vice-President of the Institute under the reorganization of 1953.
    Arrangement note
    Arranged in alphabetical and chronological order
    - Berry, George Packer, 1937-1950; 45 items (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Research on Shope papilloma virus; grant recommendations personnel recommendations.
    - Bibliographies (Box 1)
      Arranged in alphabetical order.
      - Baumgartner, Leona, 1926-1934
      - Cole, Rufus, 1901-1939
      - Goebel, Walther F., 1922-1943
      - Hoagland, Charles, 1933-1940
      - Hotchkiss, Rollin, 1936-1942
      - MacLeod, Colin, 1936-1941
      - Rothbard, Sidney, 1938-1945
    - Cohn, Alfred Einstein, 1937-1954; 104 items (Box 1)
      Deals with appointments of assistants; gifts of books from A.E. Cohn to T.M. Rivers; resignation from Journal Club.
    - Gasser, Herbert S., 1953-1956; 10 items (Box 1)
    - Goodner, Kenneth, 1937-1955; 32 items (Box 1)
    - Horsfall, Frank, 1953-1955; 10 items (Box 1)
    - Insull, William, 1952-1958; 23 items (Box 1)
      Includes original application and correspondence with F. Horsfall
    - Miscellaneous file (Box 1)
      Jacobs, Walter
      Hervey, John
      Little, Ralph
      McGhee, R. Barclay
      MacInnes, Duncan
      McIntyre, A.K.
      Morgan, Herbert R.
      Olitsky, P.K.
      Rail, Wilfred
      Stimson, George
      Stahr, G.E.
      Stone, John
      Terry, W.
      Travers, H.
      Urick, Harry
      Volk, B. W
      Willis, W.H.
      Yoeli.
    - Murphy, George Edward, 1948-1953; 34 items (Box 1)
    - Pearce, Louise, 1954-1956; 6 items (Box 1)
    - Rhoads, Cornelius P., 1942-1959; 10 items (Box 1)
    - Selective Service data, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
      Includes completed questionnaires on individual physicians.
    - Smadel, Joseph, 1940-1951; 22 items (Box 1)
      Includes recommendation for NAS membership.
    - Swift, Homer F., 1937-1953; 41 items (Box 1)
      Includes Memorial Minute written by A.R. Dochez.
    - Van Slyke, Donald, 1939-1949; 74 items (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1962 (Box 1)
    Photocopies
    Arranged in chronological order by number of medical record.
  - Applications for staff appointments with correspondence, 1945-1955; 1 box
    Applications for staff appointment in the Hospital both declined and accepted. Includes recommendations for staff appointment, letters of appointment or reappointment, some resignations and some recommendations for positions on leaving The Rockefeller Institute.
    - Applications for appointment, declined (Box 2)
      Badizadeh, Hahn, Koenigstein, Kreiter, Livingston, Loera, Machado, Meisels, Munoz, Platcou, Stein, Tomiyasu, Unhanand, Yoshino.
    - Applications for staff appointments made (Primarily Guest Investigators) (Box 2)
      Alivisatos, Spy. Ger. Anast., Allen, Raymond Archie, Anderson, Harold Clifford, Asano, Tomoaki, Archetti, Italo, Bailey, John Leggett, Barrnett, Russell J., Baxter, James Hubert, Bjorkman, Sven Erik, Blankenhorn, David Henry, Blondheim, Solomon Hillel, Bongiovanni, Alfred M., Borgström, Bengt, Brattsten, Inger Maria nee Bergdahl, Bronner, Felix, Camber, Bernard, Caulfield, James Benjamin, Chinard, Francis P., Cluff, Leighton, Cotzias, George Constantin, Dahl, Lewis Kitchener, Daly, Marie, Davenport, Fred Marshall, Despopoulos, Agememnon, Di Ferrante, Nicola, Eder, Howard A., Eisenmenger, William J., Feinstein, Alvan Richard, Foresman, Claes Olaf, Franklin, Edward C., Genest, Jacques, Giges, Burton, Ginsherg, Harold S., Good, Robert A., Greif, Roger Louis, Gros, Francois, Hardy, Paul Harold, Heinze, Kurt, Hilleman, Maurice R., Hunt, Carlton C., Itoh, Shinji, Kaufman, Edwin Hillel, Kilbourne, Edwin Dennis, Kimmelman, Leonard Jacob, Kuhns, William Joseph, Lahelle, Oskar Henry, Lauson, Henry Dumke, Leigh, Frederick Winston, McMurray, Virginia Marion, Mogabgab, William J., Moss, Arthur J., Mueller, Paul, Norman, Philip Sidney, Osawa, Syozo, Pappas, George, Pray, Alfred Rogers, Presland, John Richard, Ritts, Roy Ellot, Robbins, William Clinton, Rogers, David Elliott, Roof, Betty Sams, Rudzinska, Maria, Sager, Ruth, Sauve, Gaston, Schwartz, Irving Leon, Sedar, Albert W., Silver, Lawrence, Slater, Robert James, Smith, John MacLean, Sotelo, Jose Roberto, Sprague, James Mather, Stall, Bernard George, Stetson, Chandler Alton, Sullivan, Walter James, Taylor, Harriett E., Teng, Chih Chiang, Tezok, Fethi, Thaysen, Jørn Christian H., Thorn, Mels Anker, Todd, E.W., Tsaltas, Theodore, Tyrrell, David Arthur John, Uziel, Mayo, Vanden Schrieck, Henry G., Van der Want, J.P.H., Walker, Duard Lee, Wallenius, Gunnar, Wannamaker, Lewis William, Watson, Michael Lasell, Weisiger, James, Wiberg, George Stuart.
  - NaMRU #2 correspondence, 1943 October-1945 December; 1 box (6 folders 2 envelopes)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Received or inventoried: March, 1977
    Late in 1941 Dr. Rivers organized a research unit for the United States Navy at The Rockefeller Institute Hospital, for the treatment of Navy-personnel suffering from certain specified diseases which were to be studied and which fit into the research program of the Institute Hospital. The diseases included streptococcus infections, cirrhosis of the liver and hepatitis.
    In October 1943 Dr. Rivers visited the South Pacific and plans were made to establish a Naval Medical Research Unit Laboratory on Guam, in order to study diseases of the area in preparation for health needs of the Navy.
    Arranged in chronological order.
    Primarily the correspondence of Thomas Milton Rivers with various correspondents.
    - 1945 April 4-July 1945 August-December, 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      Matters at the Institute Hospital; return to civilian life and job opportunities for various personnel; Winthrop Rockefeller at RIH; hepatitis work; cirrhosis of the liver; personnel matters; shipments through the Institute of mice and various preparations needed for research.
      Correspondents include: J. Bronfenbrenner, Alfred E. Cohn, Homer C. Curtis, Herbert S. Gasser, Charles Hoagland, Frank Horsfall, Eugene Opie, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Homer Swift, Shields Warren, Armine T. Wilson.
    - Report on trip to the South Pacific in connection with the establishment of a research laboratory in that area, 1943 October-November; 17 pp. draft and 19 pp. carbon copy of corrected copy. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Include itinerary and tentative roster of officers and personnel.
    - Correspondence, 1943 December-1945 March (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Correspondents include: Richard Shope, W.M. Quigley, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., R.W. Babione, T.J. Carter.
    - Letter from D.D. Van Slyke on keeping Lee Farr in laboratory to continue experimental work on blood plasma, 1944 October 11 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Report by Thomas S. Hershey, Medical Problems in a Civilian Camp, 1945 February 11; 5 pages (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Forwarded by James J. Sapero, Comdr.
    - Correspondence with John D. Rockefeller, Jr. deals with injury received in action by Winthrop Rockefeller (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1945 April 2-October (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Deals with NaMRU #2 administration on Guam.
      Correspondents include: P.M. Albright, S. Bayne-Jones, F.S. Cheever, William J. Clench, Alvin F. Coburn, L.T. Coggeshall, Richard W. Coleman, E.G. Hakansson, Chester S. Keefer, C.J. Lamb, Karl F. Meyer, Stuart Mudd, J.F. Neuberger, Basil O'Connor, Harry Plotz, J.D. Rockefeller, Jr., J.J. Sapero, Richard E. Shope, A.T. Wilson, Walter L. Winkenwerder.
      Items of special interest are listed below.
      Arranged in chronological order by date of T.M. Rivers reply.
      - Report on tests with DDT Aerosol Bombs, 1945 June 1
      - To Edwin Cohn from T.M. Rivers to obtain fibrinolysin for patient treatment, 1945 June 19
      - Correspondence and enclosures between Stuart Mudd and T.M. Rivers on 4th International Congress for Microbiology and question of election of a president to arrange the Congress, 1945 June 20 (with 15 August 1945)
      - Correspondence and enclosures between Winthrop Rockefeller and T.M. Rivers, 1945 July 1 (with 11 June 1945)
        Includes 5 page holograph from Winthrop.
      - Correspondence and enclosures from McQuarrie, I. to T.M. Rivers regarding, revision of chapter in Brennemann's Practice of Pediatrics, 1945 July 25
    - Correspondence from Commander Richard E. Shope To Medical Officer in Command: T.M. Rivers. Report on Activities of First Echelon of NaMRU #2, 13 pages (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence from Richard E. Shope. Report on Participation by NaMRU #2 in Okinawa invasion (Box 3, Folder 6)
      80 pages and line map of areas in Okinawa in which observations were made.
    - Photographic prints from South Pacific, 8 prints in Envelope 1; 9 prints in Envelope 2. (Box 3)